A few years ago, I sent them the following email: "Dear brothers, I hope this message finds you well. I am emailing to let you know that I'm dropping out of my master's program in engineering to pursue a career as a full-time musician. All that I ask from you is not to worry about me." Brother number one replied. He was encouraging but a bit skeptical. He said, "I wish you the best of luck. You're going to need it." (Laughter) Brother number two was a little bit more skeptical. He said, "Don't do it! This will be the worst mistake of your life. Find a real career." (Laughter) Well, the rest of my brothers were so enthusiastic about my decision, they didn't even respond. (Laughter) I know that the skepticism coming from my brothers is out of care and concern for me. They were worried. They thought it would be difficult to make it as an artist, that it will be a challenge. And you know what? They were right. It is such a challenge to be a full-time artist.
Hace unos años, les envié el siguiente correo electrónico: "Queridos hermanos, espero que se encuentren bien. Les escribo para informarles que me saldré de la maestría en ingeniería para estudiar música a tiempo completo. Lo único que les pido es que no se preocupen por mí". El primero en responder me apoyaba pero estaba un poco escéptico. Dijo: "Te deseo la mejor de las suertes. Vas a necesitarla". (Risas) Mi otro hermano fue un poco más escéptico. Me dijo: "¡No lo hagas! O será el peor error de tu vida. Encuentra una carrera de verdad". (Risas) Bueno, mis otros hermanos estaban tan entusiasmados con mi decisión que ni siquiera respondieron. (Risas) Sé que el escepticismo de mis hermanos no es algo que deba importarme. Ellos estaban preocupados. Pensaron que sería difícil ser artista, que sería un reto. Y, ¿saben qué? Tenían razón. Es un gran reto ser artista a tiempo completo.
I have so many friends who need to have a second job as a plan B in order to pay for the bills, except that plan B sometimes becomes their plan A. And it's not just my friends and I who experience this. The US Census Bureau states that only 10 percent of art school graduates end up working as full-time artists. The other 90 percent, they change careers, they work in marketing, sales, education and other fields. But this is not news, right? We almost expect the artist to be a struggling artist. But why should we expect that? I read an article in the "Huffington Post" saying that four years ago, the European Union
Tengo muchos amigos que necesitan un segundo empleo, un plan B para cubrir sus gastos, pero a veces ese plan B se convierte en plan A. Y no nos pasa solo a mis amigos y a mí. Según la Oficina del Censo de EE.UU., solo el 10 % de los graduados en arte consigue empleo a tiempo completo como artista. El otro 90 % cambia de carrera, trabaja en mercadotecnia, ventas, educación y otros campos. Pero esto no es nuevo, ¿cierto? Casi damos por hecho que un artista se las ve difíciles. Pero, ¿por qué lo damos por hecho? Leí un artículo en el "HuffPost" que decía que hace cuatro años, la Unión Europea
began the world's largest ever arts funding initiative. Creative Europe will give 2.4 billion dollars to over 300,000 artists. In contrast, the US budget for our National Endowment for the Arts,
comenzó la iniciativa de financiación de las artes más grande del mundo. "Europa creativa" dará USD 2400 millones a más de 300 000 artistas. En contraste, el presupuesto de EE.UU. para el Fondo Nacional de las Artes,
the largest single funder for the arts across the United States, is merely 146 million dollars. To put things into perspective, the US budget for the military marching bands alone is almost twice as much as the entire NEA. Another striking image comes from Brendan McMahon for the "Huffington Post," saying that out of the one trillion dollar budget for military and defense-related spending, if only 0.05 percent were allocated to the arts, we would be able to pay for 20 full-time symphony orchestras at 20 million dollars apiece, and give over 80,000 artists an annual salary of 50,000 dollars each. If that's only 0.05 percent, imagine what a full one percent could do. Now, I know we live in a capitalist society, and profits matter a lot. So let's look at it from a financial angle, shall we? The US nonprofit arts industry generates more than 166 billion dollars in economic activity, it employs 5.7 million people and it returns 12.6 billion dollars
el único proveedor de fondos para las artes en EE.UU., es de solo USD 146 millones. Poniendo las cosas en perspectiva, el presupuesto de EE.UU. solo para las bandas de marcha militares es de casi el doble de todo el fondo nacional de las artes. Otra imagen sorprendente viene de Brandan McMahon en el "HuffPost" cuando dice que de un presupuesto de un billón de dólares para gastos militares y de defensa, si solo el 0,05 % fuera otorgado a las artes, podríamos pagar 20 orquestas sinfónicas a tiempo completo en USD 20 millones cada una, y darle a más de 80 000 artistas un salario anual de USD 50 000 a cada uno. Si eso es solo el 0,05 %, imaginen lo que se podría hacer con un porcentaje completo. Sé que vivimos en una sociedad capitalista, y las ganancias importan mucho. Así que veámoslo desde una perspectiva financiera, ¿está bien? La industria no lucrativa de las artes de EE.UU. genera más de USD 166 000 millones en actividad económica, da empleo a 5,7 millones de personas y tiene un retorno de USD 12 600 millones
in tax revenue. But this is only a financial angle, right? We all know that the arts is way more than just an economic value. The arts brings meaning to life. It's the spirit of our culture. It brings people together and it supports creativity and social cohesion. But if the arts contributes this much to our economy, why then do we still invest so little in arts and artists? Why do more than 80 percent of our schools nationwide still experience budget cuts in arts education programs? What is it about the value of arts and artists that we still don't understand? I believe the system is flawed and far from being fair, and I want to help change that. I want to live in a society
en ingresos fiscales. Esto solo desde la perspectiva financiera. Todos sabemos que las artes son mucho más que un mero valor económico. Las artes le dan sentido a la vida. Son el espíritu de nuestra cultura. Unen a la gente y fomentan la creatividad y la cohesión social. Pero si las artes contribuyen tanto a nuestra economía, ¿entonces por qué aún se invierte tan poco en ellas y en los artistas? ¿Por qué más del 80 % de nuestras escuelas en el país aún sufren reducciones monetarias en programas de educación para las artes? ¿Es que acaso aún no entendemos el valor de las artes y los artistas? Creo que el sistema es defectuoso y está lejos de ser justo, y quiero ayudar a cambiar eso. Quiero vivir en una sociedad
where artists are more valued and have more cultural and financial support so they can focus on creating arts instead of being forced to drive Ubers or take corporate jobs they'd rather not have. There are other sources of income for artists, however. There are private foundations, grants and patrons who give money, except a vast majority of artists don't know about these opportunities. On one side you have institutions and people with money. On the other side you have artists seeking funding, but the artists don't know about the people with the money, and the people with the money don't necessarily know about the artists out there. This is why I am very excited to share "Grantpa," an online platform that uses technology to match artists with grants and funding opportunities in a way that is easy, fast and less intimidating. Grantpa is only one step towards solving an existing problem of funding inequality, but we need to work collectively on multiple fronts to reevaluate how we view the artists in our society. Do we think of arts as a luxury or a necessity? Do we understand what goes on in the day-to-day life of an artist, or do we still believe that artists, no matter how struggling they are, are happy simply because they're following their passion? In a few years, I plan to send my brothers the following email: "Dear brothers, I hope this message finds you well. I am emailing to let you know that I am doing great and so are hundreds of thousands of artists who are being valued more culturally and financially and getting enough funding to focus on their crafts and create more art. I appreciate all of your support. Couldn't have done it without you." Thank you. (Applause)
donde se valore más a los artistas y donde haya más apoyo cultural y financiero para que puedan enfocarse en crear arte en vez de tener que conducir en Uber o de tener trabajos corporativos que preferirían no tomar. Hay otras fuentes de ingresos para los artistas, no obstante. Hay fundaciones privadas, becas y patrocinadores que otorgan dinero, pero una gran mayoría de artistas no saben de esas oportunidades. Por una parte, tenemos instituciones y gente con dinero. Por otra parte, tenemos artistas en busca de financiamiento. Pero los artistas no saben de la gente con dinero, y la gente con dinero no siempre sabe de los artistas que existen. Por esta razón estoy muy emocionado por compartirles "Grantpa", una plataforma en línea que usa tecnología para que los artistas busquen becas y oportunidades de financiamiento de forma fácil, rápida y menos intimidante. "Grantpa" es solo un paso para resolver el problema de la desigualdad financiera. Pero necesitamos trabajar colectivamente desde varios frentes para revaluar nuestra visión de los artistas en la sociedad. ¿Vemos a las artes como una necesidad o un lujo? ¿Comprendemos lo que ocurre en la vida diaria de un artista, o creemos que sin importar cuánto luchen los artistas deben ser felices simplemente porque hacen lo que les apasiona? En unos años, planeo enviarles a mis hermanos el siguiente correo: "Queridos hermanos, espero que se encuentren bien. Les escribo para decirles que me va muy bien a mí y también a cientos de artistas, cada vez somos más valorados cultural y financieramente y obtenemos suficientes fondos para enfocarnos en nuestro oficio y poder crear más arte. Agradezco todo su apoyo. No lo hubiera logrado sin Uds." Gracias. (Aplausos)